PRESENTER: All right.
So we're going to continue our
discussion on routing with Expo
through multiple pages.
And we're going to talk
about the use state hook
and how to make some
dynamic UI components.
So we're starting off here.
We have this index component.
That was just the
start of our app.
I'll start that up here.
So we can just get a quick
refresher where we're at.
NPM start to run metro.
I'm going to hit W, that'll pop
open this other browser tab.
And that works
exactly the same way.
If you're running
in the EC2 instance,
W should pop open
another browser tab.
The difference on your EC2
is this address bar here
is going to be local host--
instead of localhost, it's
going to be your http:// your IP
address, and then port 8081.
And we've talked about
it in class already.
But just make sure
that port 8081
is set to be allowed to
take inbound traffic there.
So we've got this
registration component.
We used react hook form.
So it'll give us some
validation while we do that.
Let's go ahead and add
another page in our app here.
So like I said,
with Expo router,
you just add pages by adding
components to the app folder
here.
That's all it takes.
So let's right-click this, and
we'll just call this component
stateDemos.jsx.
And so now we've
got a blank file
and we can go ahead and
add some logic in there.
I'm going to pop open a
GPT and grab some code.
So let's say I need a native
component for my Expo app.
And I'm going to specify that
I want it to useState hook,
let's say whether an image
is shown on the page.
All right.
And I think we-- by default,
Expo's got some images in there.
So if you go in next
to your app folder,
there's an assets folder.
And then in there's fonts
for some custom fonts
and then images.
There's a React logo.
So let's just--
I can right-click that
and copy relative path.
And I don't need it
to be an Expo app.
And make a button to
show or hide the image.
OK, so we've got--
let's copy that and we can put
it in our new component here.
So they called it
ToggleImageComponent.
I'm going to call it StateDemos.
That's fine.
And so let's look at
what we've got here.
So from React, we're
importing React.
And useState is a way
to set up a variable
and a setter for that variable.
That is usable anywhere
inside of this component.
So let's look.
Our component here is
declared as a const.
And we have the name of
our component equals.
And then we've got that fat
arrow function syntax here.
So we're defining our component
with the fat arrow function
syntax.
And everywhere in here, we
have this variable set up.
So useState and this pattern
will always be the same.
useState returns an
array-- in Python,
we call the list but an array--
with two items in it.
One is the variable and one
is a setter for that variable.
We're going to use this function
to update this variable.
And then inside of useState,
you pass it-- you don't have to,
but you can pass
it a default value.
So this is defaulting to false.
And then in our
return statement,
every component has
a return statement
to declare the UI that's there.
So we have a view that's
wrapping our image and button.
And then we have these
curly brackets here.
So whenever you're going
to write a component
right in the jsx
structure here, you
can write it in just like that.
It's usually has a
closing tag like this.
But if you need to
dynamically render it
or you need some
code logic in there,
you're going to open up
with these curly brackets.
And then we have the
variable name here
and then this ampersand syntax.
All this is doing is
checking that this is true.
And if it is, render what's
inside of these parentheses,
which is just this image.
This is kind of a JavaScript
shorthand for an if statement.
So this is similar to if
you were going to write
if is image visible whatever.
And then.
turn your image.
That's not how we write
it, but that's the idea.
This ampersand is just
shorthand for if this is true,
then render this image.
And then we've
got a button here.
The button has a title prop.
And then if-- we're checking
that variable again--
if is image visible then
the text for our title prop
is going to be hide image.
And if this is false, then
it's going to be show image.
And then we have an onPress prop
for our button, which is just
going to call the
setter here and set it
to whatever our the previous
variable value was not.
So the exclamation here is not.
So whatever in a true
false with a Boolean,
this is just flipping it
to be the other way around.
So we can go ahead and
see how that looks.
Actually we can't
because we need
to be able to navigate there.
So now that we have
this component,
we have an extra screen here.
We can see-- we've got our--
sorry for the flash bang.
This is light mode, switch that.
So we've got our
first page here.
But there's no navigation
functionality to get there.
So we've got to--
let's go over to our
index component again.
Down at the bottom, we had
this button to submit the form.
Let's just copy that quickly.
Let's say go to State Demos.
And onPress, this is--
let's say navigate
to StateDemos.
And we don't need to
pass any arguments.
So this function
doesn't exist, but let's
write it real quick
outside of the render,
or the return statement here.
So outside of this.
Don't need any arguments.
And in here, we're going to
navigate using Expo router.
So the way we do that is we're
going to call router.push.
And we're going to give
it our screen name.
And in this case,
this name needs
to match exactly
what the file name is
that we want to navigate to.
And it is case-sensitive.
But you don't need to
add the .jsx or .tsx.
Leave that off.
And router-- oops.
Router doesn't exist
yet in this file.
We haven't defined it.
So up at the top,
router equals useRouter.
And it's going to try and
help us out there import that
from Expo router.
If your IDE doesn't detect
what you're trying to do
and you're trying
to write that in,
useRouter is always
from Expo router
because that's where our
routing functionality is.
You can also just put your
whole component to ChatGPT
and tell it to add the
button or use your inline AI
assistant to add a button to.
So we've got this button
with the onPress method.
And that should
navigate there for us.
OK, so I did a silly.
What I've done here-- and
this gets everybody, trust me.
In the onPress, I'm returning--
I'm calling navigateToStateDemos
instead of just
passing it the function.
So what this is doing is it's
trying to call this function
and return the result of
that function to onPress.
But we don't want to do that.
We just want to pass the
function itself to onPress.
So I'm not going
to call it there.
And there we go.
And they're squished together.
We could put a view or
some padding or margin
in between them so that they
aren't squished, but should
be able to click that now.
And couldn't find it.
It's a nice error
boundary screen though.
What have I missed there?
Maybe I do need the slash.
Yep.
OK.
So I just needed there
at the end of the name.
So now we have this new page.
And if I click that button, then
it'll show or hide the image.
And again, that is just
running off of this--
keeping track of this variable
within the useState function.
So why do we useState?
It's a hook that
is optimized to run
in React components in this
UI any time that a state
variable or a variable that's
tracked with useState updates,
anytime that updates the
browser is going to re-render
this screen, or at least it'll
re-render this component and any
of its children that depend
on the variable that updated.
So in this case,
this return statement
has this variable in it.
So we're going to re-render
this whole component.
But let's say we had this
component nested inside
of another screen or
some other component,
we might not want to
re-render that entire screen,
especially if our app
is complex and there
are some components that are
costly in terms of performance
to render.
We only want to
re-render the portion
of that screen that needs to.
That's why we use useState.
This will optimize the
rerendering of our app
whenever our data changes.
So let's go ahead and get
some other examples here.
So I edited this a little bit
from what they recommended.
And so it's decided to
rename that component.
That way it knows what
we're dealing with here.
Let's add some other
use cases for useState.
I want to have a counter with
increment and decrement buttons.
What else can we show?
I want a text input
and a button that adds
the text to a dynamic list.
Here's the enhanced version.
I guess we are enhancing.
We're adding things to it.
Got all these nice
inline comments
to walk us through
what it's writing here.
OK.
Let's go ahead and copy that.
Boom, and I think that--
yeah, name is still the same.
So let's look at
what we've got here.
Remember AI is good, 90%
of the time, I feel like.
But you do need to be able
to read and check their work.
For things this simple, it's
usually pretty straightforward.
That's interesting.
It's trying-- oh, I don't
think you need to specify
this in regular JavaScript.
Yeah, it's trying to
do TypeScript for us.
So it's saying that useState
is declaring a string array.
But this is-- we're
using jsx here, not tsx.
We're not using TypeScript.
So we don't need that.
So we have our ImageVisible
toggle, like we did before.
We have a counter
useState variable,
which is going to initiate
at the value of 0.
And we have a text
and we have some items
which is in an array or a list.
In JavaScript, they're
called an array.
And then we have a
handler or a function
to handle adding
items to the list.
So let's go ahead and let's
first see how that renders.
Metro is still running.
So we should be able to.
Wow, look at that there.
The layout is kind of fun.
So that show image still works.
We can increment and
decrement that counter.
And then if we want to
write some text in here.
And we can type that in.
And we're adding these text
items to this list down here.
All right.
So let's look at--
the image toggle is the same.
We have IsImageVisible
variable there
that's tracking whether or
not this image is rendered.
The counter section has
text which says counter.
And then this is
with these brackets,
that's how you get some
code logic in there.
So it normally inside
of text, whatever
is in between the
two text tags, this
is your text that's going to
be rendered in there directly.
But we have a dynamic
piece of text in this case.
So we're going to wrap that
in these curly brackets.
And then just put the
variable right in there.
And in this case, the
variable is the counter value
that we have set up
here with useState.
So that's how it's updating
that counter text dynamically.
And then we've got some onPress
props here for our buttons.
And that just set--
they call set counter.
And we're getting the previous
counter value plus 1 or minus 1.
Simple enough.
And then we have a text input.
Text input, again, this is just
imported from React Native.
All of these are imported
from React Native.
We don't have any sort of
special UI library involved yet.
Then we've got this text input,
takes a style placeholder text.
And then the value
is this text value.
So this is actually one that we
are also tracking with useState.
So anytime that text changes,
we have access to whatever
the text is right here.
And then we're setting the text.
We're passing this to
the onChange Handler
to set the text.
So the value of our text input
here is tracked by useState.
And so the text input
can track that for us.
This is also useful.
Like if we have a custom
form validation function,
we can define that function.
And we have access
to that text variable
anywhere that we need it.
And then we have this button.
Button has an onPress
handler, addItemToList.
And that's calling text.trim.
And that trims the
white space like spaces,
or enter new line
characters from the text.
And then it's calling setItems,
which is the setter in useState
to set the items.
Or let's see, it's
setting the array of items
to a new array with all of
the previous items in it,
as well as text.trim.
Oh yeah.
So it's calling it here
to see if it's valid text,
and then it's actually trimming
it and adding it to the list
there.
And then it's calling
setText to an empty string.
So it's resetting the
text in that text input.
All of that's handled
with useState.
That's an example of how
we can get some dynamic UI
elements here.
The benefit is useState
is highly optimized
to work in React apps.
The downside is,
let's say you wanted
to know what some of
the data from this page
is over on this page,
you don't have access
to any of those useState
variables in here.
That is what redux is for.
We will go into using redux
a little bit more next week.
We'll start into that next week.
Redux is-- it functioned
very much the same way
as useState does.
You have your variables and
a way to set those variables.
But the redux
variables are available
throughout our entire app.
So useState is for managing
state within a single component.
We will use redux to manage
state throughout the entire Expo
app.
We'll be getting
into that next week.
So we have this code that's
dynamically powering our UI here
on our page.
I'm going to toggle the dark
off hold for flash bang.
So this is what
the UI looks like.
But I think we can do
a little bit better.
And a good way to make
sure that across our apps
and across our pages, that
we have a consistent UI
is to use some sort of design
system or component library
that we use throughout our apps.
Some people, some organizations
will make their own.
They'll have in there--
they'll have a components
folder full of a bunch of text
components, let's say they
have a view or a button
or their text that is
styled a certain way.
They want it to be consistent
throughout the app.
People may make their own.
Where I work at JB Hunt, we have
our own in-house design system.
So our brand has a
unique look and feel.
And all of those
UI components are
used throughout the
different JB Hunt apps.
For example, I work
on the carrier team.
Carrier is an external
user-facing app,
but we also have internal facing
apps like the drive app or match
or there's the shipper app.
That's another
externally facing app.
All of them use-- or
at least most of them--
all use the same aim
component library.
Some of the apps, like
Carriers, are a little bit older
and hasn't fully adopted
the new component library
that we've built in-house.
But for the most
part, our apps are
expected to use a common
component library.
So we have a consistent
look and feel.
You could make your own
component library here
for your app in this class or
that usually takes a long time.
So one that I recommend that
you can use here in this class
is react-native-paper.
This has been my favorite
component library for a minute,
mainly because it works well
with React Native cross-platform
apps.
And it also it supports
web and mobile.
It's kind of hard
to find a component
library that will support
web and mobile for React.
But it does a pretty good job.
So let's go ahead and grab--
we haven't made
any edits to this.
So it should still be
fresh in our GPT's memory.
Let's rewrite that page using
react-native-paper components.
And while it's
generating that, we'll
say for react-Native-paper, they
do have demo apps that are fun.
You can go ahead and go to the
Google Play store or the iOS
Store.
And there's an app, you
can just download it.
It doesn't do anything.
It just has all the
different components
you can play around with.
Toggle their buttons and
open pages and cards and such
to see different UI components
in action on their website.
You can see they've got
the link to their GitHub,
and you can literally-- you
can just comb through and see
the code in their examples,
their integrations with React
navigation.
And then they've got their Docs.
And here you can search
for-- let's say you're
interested in using their card.
Then you can just look at how
they use their card component
right in there in
the documentation.
I think it should be
done at that point.
And then do keep in mind,
this is another node module.
So let's go ahead and copy that.
And going to kill
the metro server.
Anytime you install
a new node module,
you will need to
stop and restart
your metro bundler anyway.
And then NPM start that
back up again and let's
go grab that code, copy.
And then we should see
our import statements.
We don't have as many things
imported from React Native
anymore.
Just a view.
View will always be
from React Native.
And then the FlatList
and StyleSheet component.
Everything else is now--
all of our other UI elements
are coming from React Native
paper, which is what you want.
If you're going to
use a design system,
you want to use it in as
many places as possible.
You don't want to mix like React
Native paper text component
with a React Native text
component in the same page.
You want to be consistent.
So let's see how that
looks with it updated.
And it doesn't know that
we're not using TypeScript.
So let's remove that.
I'm surprised that's the
only TypeScript annotation
that this file needed.
Let's go to that second page.
And it looks very purple.
I know you can change like
your accent, colors and theme
and such in React Native paper.
And we've got our increment
and decrement counters.
Let's see.
You can see the text input,
there is material design
adjacent.
All right.
So yep, that's the new UI.
Let's keep our
whole app consistent
and update our other page
to do the same thing.
Put that in there.
And then there's
one other thing.
If you're using React Native
paper that will need to do--
I wonder if it actually-- if it
would have mentioned the paper
provider.
Let's see.
No, it's still rendering,
still generating.
OK.
Looks like we're done there.
Copy paste.
Put that in there and
then we can go back.
So I found out what was
causing the issue before.
So we had this picker
component that was not using
React Native paper before.
So when I asked it to convert
the form to React Native paper,
React Native paper actually
doesn't have a picker type
component in its components
library, which is honestly
the biggest complaint I have
about that UI library before,
because pickers are such
a common form element.
I've run into this before.
They do have a menu and some
other things you can substitute
it with, but when I--
so anyway, it tried to use
another drop down component
and try to import it from
React Native paper at first.
And then I called it out on
this and I was like, hey,
this isn't working.
And it's like, oh yeah, I
suggested a conceptual approach
earlier, but this might
be causing an issue.
So it's like, yeah,
that doesn't exist.
So that is one issue that
will come up occasionally
with using GenAI, is they can
hallucinate or make up solutions
to problems that
don't actually exist.
But I did a bit of
searching on GitHub and I
found a project that includes--
uses React hook form and React
Native paper to build forms.
And it's this FormBuilder
component or this FormBuilder--
yeah, a FormBuilder component.
And basically you just pass it
all of your form configuration
items like what formed
items with the labels
are what the validation
is going to be,
and it just spits
out a form for you.
Kind of fun.
You might notice, though,
this is not the same color
as the rest of our web page.
And the reason for that
is because the FormBuilder
is trying to be extra helpful.
If you pop open
your system settings
and if you're running
this app on Android,
this would be your
Android settings.
If you're running this on iOS,
that would be your iOS settings.
I'm running on Linux.
Windows, Mac would do this, too.
All operating systems nowadays
have a theme picker of sorts.
There we go.
And they'll support a
light and a dark theme.
And I had dark theme selected.
If I switch to light
theme, then you
can see this form automatically
updates to light theme.
And React Native provides
a use theme context hook.
So you can hook into--
your application can hook
into your systems
theme settings.
So you can dynamically
or automatically
set dark theme or light theme
based on what your user's system
settings are.
So you already have their
preference available that way.
Anyway, you can find
projects on GitHub.
I don't know if I'll
keep using this or not.
It seems pretty simple to
use, but you can use it--
you can use different projects
on GitHub or different node
modules, depending on what
your project requirements are.
One other thing
that we need to do
if you're using React Native
paper is to use a provider.
So if we pop over
to our layout.jsx,
and I actually already put this
in there, but I'll revert this.
So it's like it was before.
We just had a route
layout that was returning
a stack that rendered--
this automatically renders our
index component by default.
What a provider
is, is it provides
context for, in this
case, React Native paper.
And what that's doing is any
component that you end up
rendering in your app,
any page or any component
inside those pages will
all be able to have access
to the same theme context.
React Native paper has a
light theme by default.
But if you wrap your app
in this paper provider
and then you want to use
the React Native paper theme
settings to change your accent
colors or your light or dark
theme, then the entire
component or the entire app
will be able to
have access to that
without you having to update
every one programmatically.
We'll use providers again later
in Expo projects or any React
or React Native project.
Specifically, we're
going to use one
for Redux, which I've
talked about previously.
That is just a global
state management solution,
and we'll need a provider so
that all of our components
can have access to
that provider data.
So go ahead and give this
a shot with your project.
In order to meet the
homework requirements,
you will need to
use useState hook
and have some sort of dynamic
component rendering in your app,
whether that's toggling
some UI elements
or having a data driven list
or some other set of data.
And anything, any UI that
changes based on data
will benefit from the
use of a useState hook.
So that will sum it up.
Go ahead and leave your
questions in Teams,
or message me in
Canvas, and we'll
keep working on our projects.